[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gregory cap Hammer
today's guest is Jonathan Schneider a
co-founder of mad and the creator of
open rewrite he is the author of two
books published by O'Reilly focusing on
topics like Sr with Java microservices
and automated code remediation Jonathan
welcome to the show thank you Gregor
it's a pleasure to be here during this
episode we will be talking about open
rewrite we're going to start the
conversation by exploring what open
rewrite is and the problems that it
solves Jonathan let's begin by
discussing the following question what
is automated refactoring and what are
its benefits automated refactoring is is
writing software that rewrites other
software and its main benefits are to
achieve some modernization in that
software to fix security
vulnerabilities and to ensure a
consistent style or fix these
inconsistencies in COD bases and if I'm
understanding correctly open rewrite is
an automated refactoring tool is that
the right way to think about it it is
open rewrite you can think of as a
combination of two things it's a rich
set of data about a cbase so not just
the text but more information that the
compiler would know as well and then
programs called recipes that operate on
that data to make changes to the c-base
at large thanks for that response we're
going to talk about recipes later in the
episode what I wanted to do quickly is
to learn a little bit more about how you
know an automated refactoring is correct
so can you talk a little bit about that
what does a software engineer need to do
do in order to ensure that open rewrite
worked the right way sure the
correctness really stems from some of
the characteristics of that data that we
mentioned earlier so we're all used to
operating and working with the text of
code but the first thing a compiler will
do with a text of code is to take it and
turn it into what's called an abstract
syntax tree so it turns it into this
tree structure the word syntax in the
middle of that is interesting because
it's it's really just the structure
of the code so where is a variable
declaration where is there a class
declaration a method declaration Etc it
then takes that a and goes to a second
phase whereby it goes through that
syntax tree and tries to solve for all
these names that it found when it sees a
method what was the type that that
method was defined on when it sees a
variable what is the type of that
variable and so it'll put information
about that we call that type attribution
on the tree if if I'm then doing a
refactoring on the syntax of code say I
want to change a logger statement logger
doino then just the word info isn't
enough for me to be confident that that
method came from a particular logotype
it's when a recipe is able to use the
type attribution information that the
compiler knows that this info method
comes from a particular type that
were're able to make that change so type
attribution is one of the Essential
Elements of correctness in a recipe but
there's actually a soft form of
correctness as well which is interesting
which is that if we're going to make a
change in a code base and suggest it to
a user or to an engineer on that project
it needs to look stylistically
consistent in the context of that code
base now you may be running a one recipe
across multiple repositories that have
Divergent Styles one uses tabs and
spaces because of course we're never
going to agree on that different import
ordering formats Etc
so open rewrite is designed to discover
the style of the project theistically
from its existing style and massage a
change to look idiomatically consistent
in context and so it's really those two
things together the compilable
correctness and also the fact that the
change follows the stylistic idiom of
the project around it thank you for that
response that was really helpful I think
compilable correctness makes a lot of
sense because obviously if I refactor my
code and it no longer compiles
then I'm really in big trouble that's
right you haven't done much so we're
going to talk quite a bit more about
recipes and syntax trees and the types
that you referred to a moment ago let me
ask another perhaps obvious question but
many people might have done a little bit
of automated refactoring where they
simply use something like a regular
expression why are things like regular
Expressions not suitable for automated
refactoring we tried really hard when we
started this project
open rewrite at Netflix about 8 years
ago to make a change to an internal
logging Library we had a internal
Library called Blitz for J which we came
to regret we should have just used slf
for J so we were trying to transition
from one to the other they were very
similar in structure but the string
literal the first argument of the logger
statement used a different
parameterization syntax and the
exception occurred first than last and
so we were just trying to use regular
Expressions to find these statements and
Shuffle these parameters around and it
just got very very difficult because as
you can imagine the first string
argument to a loging statement may
actually be a concatenation of multiple
strings over multiple lines the
exception could be a method call it
could be a new class it got very
difficult to accommodate all the
variation that existed in the code that
makes a lot of sense so essentially
unless we use an automated refactoring
tool that is able to speak the language
of a tree then we're really not going to
be able to ensure that we have
correctness in our automated refactoring
that's right thank you for that what I
want to do now is just briefly comment
on the language that you chose to
implement open rewrite can you comment
on that briefly it is written in Java or
originally is written in Java because it
did come out of Netflix and that
organization used Java predominantly on
the back end so most of the thousands of
microservices were written in Java okay
and I know that Java developers can use
open rewrite what are the various
programming languages that open rewrite
supports in terms of automated
refactoring we started in the jvm for
that reason because that's where
Netflix's code was predominantly and
started to move from there in two
different directions one in the sard
direction also let's take care of our
infrastructure code so that could be
Json yaml terraform HCL properties files
text files these kinds of things so you
can refactor with that as well and then
in a different direction it started
extending from java into groovy and into
cotland those are supported really well
right now and from there actually added
a Cobalt or zos parser now we're adding
uh C parser in the next 30 days roughly
and we already have open source
implementations of JavaScript and python
although I expect those to change
somewhat before they're they're fully GA
based on how we we view supporting other
languages right now there's one
interesting thing that we discovered as
we started to write the parsers for
JavaScript for python for C is that at
the LST level that lossless semantic
tree so that's that syntax plus all the
type attribution information I hadn't
given a name to it earlier at the tree
level JavaScript and Python and Java and
groovy and cotlin are largely the same
in the sense that they have the same
elements a method declaration variable
decoration they look very different in
syntax when you actually print them out
to text but structurally they're very
similar and so when we went to write the
JavaScript parser we actually made it
extend J the base Java LST when we went
to write C we made it extend J the base
Java LST such that many of the building
block recipes that we wrote like change
method name and change method to St
Target to static those kinds of things
actually work on both languages without
having to rewrite them wow that's really
interesting I heard you mentioned
several times the word parser can you
comment briefly what are the inputs and
outputs of a parser and how do these
parsers fit into open rewrite sure a
parser is what we use to take the text
of code and turn it into that lossless
seman IC tree and the inputs to that can
be quite complicated depending on what
the language is it isn't just the source
files or the set of source files but we
also have to understand the structure of
the project like a Java project can be
broken into multiple projects inside of
Any Given repository and those projects
have multiple Source sets those Source
sets can have different dependencies
from one another so a compiler really
needs a set of source files and its set
of binary dependencies in order to be
able to compile it and so when we
implement parsers we tend to do so by
integrating or injecting this parsing
into existing language idiomatic build
tools like Maven or Gradle so that we
can derive what the source set structure
of the project really is so at a high
level if I'm understanding you correctly
I think that the input to the parser is
the Java program or the C program is the
output of the parser some type of tree
based intermediate representation it
really is that's the lossless semantic
tree that's what a compiler normally
does on its steady March towards a
binary as or a compiled representation
at the end but unlike the intermediate
representation that the compiler uses
this intermediate representation is
designed just to stay there temporarily
and then be printed back out to text so
the compiler's a or its type attributed
form will have already discarded the
Whit space of the project cuz that
doesn't matter anymore the comments of
the original project cuz that doesn't
matter anymore and so we have to build a
slightly different intermediate
representation one that's purpose built
for refactoring rather than producing a
binary output at the end that makes a
lot of sense so if I'm a developer who's
using open rewrite when do I use it do I
use it on my developer laptop do I use
it in CI can you comment a little bit
about when I would actually pick up and
use open rewrite I think the answer is
yes to every workflow I think that
there's places where it's used on a
local machine where you can introduce CI
quality Gates that ensure that certain
patterns are respected inside of an
organization but I think you also need
to be prepared to act on the code base
at scale at any given moment and for
those kinds of events like a log for
shell or zero day security vulnerability
where you need to systematically go
through your codebase and discover and
remediate a particular pattern
developers tend I think to associate
code-based automation with cicd so the
first thing they'll reach for in their
mind is cicd because we've built so much
interesting Automation in that process
but we have to remember that not every
repository builds every day in fact
there can be quite some time there could
be months of time that pass for a
particular stable repository that isn't
actively being worked on so when there
is that kind of zero day event where we
have to go and look through the entire
code base we can't really rely or we
shouldn't only rely on cicd as the
machine of automation to promulgate that
change thanks for that response I think
what you have suggested means that when
I'm doing linting I might want to do
that in CI but if I'm doing a patch for
security vulnerability maybe I might do
that to my developer Workstation is that
the right way to think about it or that
you would want some mechanism to issue
Mass pole requests for those kind of Zer
day security vulnerabilities even
specific kinds of change if I was I'll
give you an example that's not security
vulnerability related whenever Gradle
releases a new version we will do a mass
commit to all of our 100 repositories to
update that to our Gradle builds to the
latest I don't want to run that even
with open rewrite I don't want to run
that recipe on a per repository basis by
having to clone each repository to my
local machine and doing that commit but
if it's a migration from Spring boot 1
to 2 to three where there could be
thousands of changes my tendency is to
want to pull repository down and apply
that recipe which itself could make
those thousands of changes and to be
able to touch it to be able to run it to
see it compile in my IDE to Poker around
the edges before I even make that PR
commit thank you those concrete examples
were super helpful let's talk briefly
about a couple of clear ways in which
people have used open rewrite so you've
already mentioned a zero day exploit can
you be very specific what are the ways
in which we would use open rewrite to
patch a security vulnerability
absolutely so the most interesting
security vulnerabilities to me are ones
where you require a combination of
depend depy and source code changes I
think the state-of-the-art for a long
time and mass automation has been things
like dependabot or renovate that just
bump dependency versions and actually
only direct dependency versions you'll
notice but that vulnerability could be
lurking in a Transit of dependency six
levels down and whose remediation
requires not only a bump in that
dependency but also a change to the code
to use it so one good example this I
think and just one of many but is this
remote code execution vulnerability and
snake Amel these poor D serialization
libraries are always subject in
additional deserialization gadgets and
so indeed snake Amel was found to have
that remote code execution and the
author did the right thing by making a
change to the Constructor to require an
argument that wasn't previously required
and then did a major version release so
went from 1.x to two that's very
difficult to just take a PR from
dependabot that bumps to two and
everything's going to be okay with the
world you really have to make code
changes as well that's a great example
thanks for sharing it I can absolutely
see why using open rewrite would be very
helpful there you're already hinting at
another thing that I wanted to talk
about I'm assuming it's pretty common to
have to do a various types of migrations
to like the new API of some type of
library or framework can you develop
that idea a little bit further how does
open read WR help with API migrations
absolutely so this is where an API
migration version going from Spring Boot
2 to three normally we look at a set of
release notes and that set of release
notes has a detailed list of all the
individual changes that you have to make
it's not just bump into new versions but
there's new idioms new patterns some of
which are suggested some of which are
required and so each of those steps we
would Implement as an open rewrite
recipe recipes eles can be composits or
holders of other recipes and so what you
wind up seeing is increasing orders of
abstraction in the recipe itself for
example moving from Spring boot 1 to 2
to three requires you to move from java
8 to 17 moving to just Java 17 from 8
requires you to first move to 11 so
you'll see this nesting of these recipes
where the first step in migrating to
spring boo 3 is to move to Java 17 but
you also have to to move to 27 first
which means you have to move to 26 first
which means you have to move to 25 24
which means you have to move from J 4 to
5 which means you have to move from Mak
to 1 to three so it's like it gets very
deeply nested that spring boot 3 recipe
as it exists right now in open source
has
1,887 steps to it that's how much change
there's been just in the last couple
years in that framework so all I have to
say is wow that's incredible and from
what I understand you're saying it
sounds like open rewrite if I use that
recipe can do all of those steps
automatically is that the right way to
think about it that's right and when we
talk about a migration like spring boot
that is such a broad ecosystem that I
think you'll find that there's some dark
corner of it that hasn't been covered
yet and folks will either contribute
additional recipes to that pile or
they'll just accept this got me 95% of
the way there and I make additional
edits and that's the end of it sure that
makes a lot of sense I think there's
another important thing about that we
haven't mentioned which is that open
reite has that word open on the front of
it and it has that word open because
it's Apache licensed and so both the
parsers that produce the LST and all the
recipes are Apache licensed the
intention is that they're usable in any
product or experience that might be
developed and it's really important I
think that these recipes are Apache
licensed because effectively we are
asking framework authors to start taking
responsibility for providing recipes
when they make breaking changes so my
expectation of the spring team is if you
break it you fix it and that if you
don't there's a competing framework like
Micronaut that does provide Auto
remediation or it's breaking changes
that that should be a decision criteria
for me as an application developer that
I want to be using Frameworks that are
going to help me move forward as they
make changes yeah that makes a lot of
sense so essentially what you're saying
is as an engineer we should pick which
Frameworks we depend on based on whether
or not they're going to help us during
the upgrade process absolutely cuz right
now a lot of our time really is spent on
this mechanical tedious work that should
be automated and that we could write
recipes for but really should also be
provided at large by the third party and
open source libraries upon which we
depend I know a lot of our listeners are
going to be interested in learning more
about how long it takes to run open
rewrite and you don't have to be overly
Concrete in this but can you give us a
rough estimate how long does it take to
run open rewrite if they were like for
example using the spring boot recipe
that you mentioned before so there's two
parts in a run with the open- source
tooling there's the production of the L
in the first place which parsing this
text code into memory and then there's
the ex execution of these recipe
programs over that LST in the open
source tooling that's the parsing step
is proportional to a clean compilation
on the project you really are running
the compiler after all behind the scenes
and there's no incremental compilation
possible there really so it's a clean
compilation and so the recipe run itself
is comparatively short relative to
parsing so we'll get into a little bit
later I think the distinction between
open reite mad but as a kind of hint
towards that understand that most of the
recipe running time is dominated by
parsing H okay that makes sense and I
can understand where you're going with
that if listeners want to learn more
about Legacy code or how to improve
Legacy code they may want to check out
software engineering radio episode 602
what I want to do now is to just pick up
on a few of the topics that you
mentioned previously so you've already
talked about how open rewrite does a
type of static analysis and then it
produces something that's called a
lossless semantic tree so let's pick up
on a couple of those comments briefly
first of all what is static analysis and
how is it different than Dynamic
analysis sure yeah static analysis is is
really studying the code base or the
tree of the code base for and
discovering facts about it that are
determinable from looking at the source
code and maybe also the information that
the compiler infers in that type
attribution information static analysis
is well known to be something where you
can have completeness or you can have
soundness so you get to choose you don't
get to have both complete and sound
analysis in many cases and to be clear
the kind of analysis that open rewrite
is doing does not require the execution
of the program is that correct that's
right okay now before you mentioned the
idea of a lossless semantic tree and
we've just been calling that the tree in
part of our conversation but what I
wanted to pick up on is your use of the
word lossless what does it mean if a
semantic tree is lossless in nature I
think what we meant and we're trying to
hint at with lossless was that the tree
could be printed back to the text of the
original code without losing any of the
original appearance of the code and also
that we didn't lose any information that
the compiler knew about in that second
intermediate rep presentation that may
be used by a recipe to make an accurate
change so why is it important for open
rewrite to use an LST I know a moment
ago you said accurate and before that
you said you want the code to reflect
the style can you comment on those
issues a little bit further I think
especially the second one the style is
something that came out of its Origins
at Netflix there I was working on
engineering tools and Netflix had the
special culture at the time called
freedom and responsibility which meant
that a central team couldn't impose any
constraints on what product Engineers
did that led to wildly Divergent Styles
between repositories in the organization
contrast that with what Google is famous
for with its monor repo and its Google
Java format and other sort of strictures
that ensure a consistency to the
codebase that's not present at Netflix
that was 20,000 repositories that look
different from one another now I find
that a large part of the world looks
more like Netflix freedom and
responsibility than it does like Google
either intentionally or accidentally it
could just be that you have 25 years of
code and you have a layer cake or
archaeology of styles or you've acquired
code through acquisition there's all
sorts of reasons but even if you want to
be highly controlled in style we find
that that's not actually really true in
most places so how does open rewrite
store and manipulate these special types
of lossless semantic trees so that's
actually again a hint towards the later
discussion in the open source open RAR
parsers actually put those trees in
memory and the recipe writes or operates
on them in memory so in effect they are
not stored they're always calculated at
the time that a recipe is running okay
and there must be something inside of
open rewrite that creates these trees I
anticipate that this is connected to
something called the visitor design
pattern can you comment on how these
visitors which you mentioned once
previously work inside of open rewrite
sure yeah the thing that produces the
tree from the text of the code is the
parser and even in implementing a parser
we're allowing the compiler to produce
its tree and then we're using the
compiler's visitor to navigate to every
component of that tree and then doing a
mapping of effectively just like a
domain mapping from an internal type to
an open rewrite type as we go down that
tree the visitor pattern in general I
think of it this is an imperfect analogy
so bear with me but I think of the
visitor pattern as almost like an
event-driven system for navigating the
tree so I may be interested in finding
logger info statements so I would be
given a tree at the top and I may
override the visit method invocation
method on the visitor because I only
want to intercept or see method
invocations I don't care about binary
concatenations I don't care about class
decorations and so it allows me to
narrow the Search scope to a particular
kind of syntax and so in that respect
it's kind of event driven but unlike an
event driven system where you're just
getting like a message bus event for
everything that's fired those visit
methods in a visitor are also
responsible for the navigation of the
tree so they will take a method
invocation for example and call visit on
the method name it'll call visit on each
argument which in turn could cause many
visitor methods to be called as well and
so by overriding when I'm writing a
recipe and I overwrite a visitor when
I'm overriding a method I'm taking
control of that navigation by calling
super on that visit method I'm allowing
the navigation to continue down the tree
further by withholding the call to Super
I'm preventing the remainder of the tree
from being navigated I control
effectively when it's called I could
look at information first or I could
call Super first and so it really is
kind of the combination of those two
things navigation plus almost like an
event driven system that was really
helpful thanks for explaining the
visitor design pattern there's one other
topic I wanted to briefly touch on it's
connected to the fact that open rewrite
has this cursor that helps you during
node visitation can you comment what is
this cursor and how do I use it as a
programmer who's leveraging open rewrite
sure the cursor itself is really just a
stack of the elements of the tree that
I've visited to the point where I've
gotten to this current event this
current thing that I'm looking at open
rewrite supports the idea of cursor
messaging which means I can put little
pieces of data on the cursor as I'm
navigating down the tree or I can put
cursor messages on an cestors of me up
the tree so that when control returns
back up in the visitor to that element
there may be data that I've found lower
level that I I use to make some sort of
change higher up so it's really just
kind of a message passing system inside
of the visitor itself that makes sense
now in a moment we're going to talk
about open rewrite and how it compares
to other tools that do static analysis
before we begin that part of our
conversation if listeners want to learn
more about static code analysis they can
listen to software engineering radio
episode 59 which we'll link to in the
show notes so let's talk about some of
the other tools that our listeners may
have heard of I anticipate that one that
they may have tried out or read about is
called Java parser so briefly Jonathan
what is Java parser and how does it
compare to open rewrite absolutely Java
parser also is a technology used to
parse Java's source code and perform
some sorts of analyses on it when I
first counter Java parser 10 or 11 years
ago I guess when this work began it had
some limited analysis or type
attribution or the ability to solve for
Types on its tree that implementation
was outside of the compiler it was in
effect a simulation of what the compiler
does at compilation time and so I think
open reite had a slightly different
starting point where it was really
started as just a data the model of the
tree and then used the compiler itself
to compile and type attribute the code
and then do that mapping exercise so it
was designed to work by mapping from
compiler internal representations rather
than mirror what the compiler did inside
okay I see now one other thing I wanted
to briefly comment on is something
called tree sitter I remember you saying
before that open rewrite has a whole
bunch of different parsers in inside of
it like for example one for Java or one
for groovy and when you were saying that
it made me think of tree sitter parsers
so how does open reite connect to use or
is it similar to tree sitter tree sitter
is mostly used to build the syntax tree
not the syntax tree with type
attribution and so in a similar respect
we could have used a antar parser to
create the structure or syntax of a Java
source file we could have used
treesitter to create the syntax or
structure of a Java source file we could
use the compiler internal first step to
produce the structure or syntax of a
file there's many different ways we
could create partial generators that or
use partial generators to create the
syntax but tritter doesn't go the next
step to do that type attribution
information so it tends to be used in
places where the analyses can be done on
the syntax tax alone yeah that's a great
point and in fact that's where I've used
treesitter the most as well essentially
it's living inside of my text editor and
it can do things like syntax
highlighting but it's not necessarily
picking up on the rich type information
and that's what I think your parsers in
open rewrite are able to pick up on and
then to leverage through the LST that's
right okay hey that was awesome now in a
moment we're going to talk about the
specifics of how we use open rewrite for
automated refactoring and that's where
going to dive into recipes and we're
going to talk about how open rewrite
connects to the m system but before we
get started are there any other
implementation details about open
rewrite that you wanted to highlight I
think we've covered what exists today I
think as we look forward to the next
couple months we mentioned this
extension into other languages and one
thing that's very important I think to
open Rite as a community as it expands
into other languages is to provide
native recipe authorship experiences in
the language that you're you're working
to refactor so I don't want a c
developer to have to write a recipe in
Java using a Java visitor using a Java
code to modify their C code and on that
level we've started and we'll open soon
a technology called remoting which
allows us to take that data that LST
model and move it across process
boundaries such that we can can actually
have recipes written in multiple
languages operating on a particular LST
I mentioned that c was also extending
the J LST so in the act of moving sayet
theet core I may have to change some
method names that recipe we already
wrote in Java so the first step in that
recipe may be modifying a c LST in a
Java process and then the next step was
written in C so the data will pass to
that c process for and a recipe written
in C will do that modification and so
this is going to be I think the first
time where there's a language level
cooperation like recipes written in Java
can benefit CP developers and vice versa
and that's a world I'm really excited
about yeah I can see why that would be
exceptional to have and you mentioned
something else that I would imagine
would be very beneficial which is if I'm
a c developer I want to write my recipes
in C as opposed to having to use Java I
think at this point we should talk a
little bit more about these recipes
because clearly they're Central to open
rewrite it sounds like there's an
ecosystem of recipes that developers can
use can you talk a little bit more about
that sure there's almost
2,500 of these now I think so it's quite
broad cover a variety of use cases
around
modernization security vulnerability
repair code quality MTI type things
what's most interesting to me about this
ecosystem is who the participants really
are and we mentioned one earlier which
is framework author so if you're a
framework author making a break and
change it's really in your interest to
provide a recipe because you're able to
move your user base forward more quickly
which means you can actually innovate
faster than you did you don't have to
hold on to these old apis quite as long
and we see security researchers writing
recipes that do remediation
there was a engineer by the name of
Jonathan Leu that issued the second most
commits of any person on GitHub in 2022
via the execution of security
vulnerability recipes he was writing and
and running and doing Mass PRS for and
so you just see different parties I
think working towards this common goal
of manipulating their codas a moment ago
you mentioned that you could have
recipes that were connected to code
quality issues what types of code
quality issues can you detect through a
recipe can you give some examples
absolutely so this could be think of the
typical sonar Cube white Source check
marks HP fortify verac code those kinds
of tools that look for code smells like
potential n pointer exceptions when the
equals is comparison to a string literal
has the literal second rather than first
and missing braces you could it could be
a wide variety of things just little
logic bugs and comparison operators so
whenever there's an existing rule like
that coming from a scanning tool like a
a sonar Cube or one of these kinds of
things and we find that that issue is
widespread in an organization we'll
basically start and write an open
rewrite recipe that not only identifies
that issue but but fixes it and that in
effect becomes a substitution for the
scanner you just go and fix that issue
at scale we were working with a Canadian
bank at one point that just looked at
sonar Cube and just picked the top five
high severity security oriented sonar
Cube rules and sonor Q provides a manual
estimate of the time it will take
developers to fix every occurrence
across their code base and sonar Cube
said it would take them 4.9 years of
developer time to fix just these five
issues right so that's five recipes not
500 it's just five recipes and an
engineer there pretty boldly actually
took those five and and a few others and
mass committed those fixes to the entire
Commercial Bank so the inside of that
day that commercial bank's code base
went from an e score in sonar Cube to an
a score in sonar Cube it's it's really
unlike anything that they had done
previously wow I have to say that's both
jaw-dropping and incredible what a great
use of the tool I'm wondering now maybe
we could use this bank as an example
what did they actually have to do to
test their recipes in order to establish
a confidence in their correctness
because clearly this was a sweeping
change across their code base yes so
recipes themselves rewrite has a a full
testing harness for testing recipes at a
unit testing harness where you
effectively Prov
before and after samples of code and run
in the unit test itself in string
literals that get syntax highlighted in
the ID and everything so you'll think
about the kinds of variations and encode
each one of those in the unit test and
like any software that we test there's
things that we think of in advance and
there's things we don't think of in
advance and so we'll unit test all the
scenarios that we imagined we'll Mass
run it on a code base we'll look for
patterns we didn't imagine which feed
back into those unit tests as additional
as additional cases to cover and over
time the quality of the recipe gets more
and more bulletproof I think that's why
it's important to be able to run
efficiently across a whole organization
when you're writing a new recipe and
before you start Distributing it to all
the product teams to be able to kind of
see the impact that it would have on the
whole organization first I'm assuming
it's possible for recipe to crash Why
would a recipe crash and then how do you
debug those recipes sure it can crash
for a variety of reasons after all
recipe is a program which I I keep going
back to it's not a query language right
it's more like a data warehouse for code
more like an old app system think of
like a snowflake that kind of thing not
like SQL just a query language so you
could throw an old pointer exception
inside of a recipe for sure the
framework itself will capture or will
trap those exceptions that happen inside
of a recipe and record on something we
call a marker which is just a piece of
data hanging on a tree node it'll record
as a marker on the tree element the
recipe crashed on the stack trace of
what actually failed so that later on
you can go and do this analysis you
could run it across hundreds of millions
of lines of code and then group all the
failures by their similarity to one
another that sounds interesting what I
wanted to do now is to turn our
attention into a very practical way in
which a developer would get started from
what I understand open rewrite has Maven
plugins and Gradle plugins how do they
use those plugins in order to run a
recipe absolutely so they would be
adding those plugins you can see this by
the way on docs. openen
that you want to run from the existing
catalog of available recipes which which
are documented there as well and then
you run a build tool command Gradle
rewrite run or Maven rewrite run and
that will do both that parsing that we
talked about earlier also run the recipe
and produce either a patch file on the
side or it will depending on the
configuration just make the change
locally on disk okay one of the things I
wanted to talk about now is the
commercial offering that is connected to
open rewrite can you talk a little bit
about what that commercial offering is
and how developers can use it sure so
what we just described there with the
build plugins is really a single
repository experience you're going in
and you're making a modification to a
build configuration and you're running a
recipe we mentioned earlier as well the
time where there was dominated by the
parsing itself where mad really comes in
is taking that LST so the really the
core piece of Ip the dividing line for
us between open source and Commercial is
really ability to take that LST model
and serialize it to dis in a compact
form and that allows us then to build
multi repository experiences so one of
the first steps we will work on inside
of an organization is to set up Mass
inest where we're cloning hundreds or
thousands or tens of thousands of
repositories and running the parsers to
produce the LST storing them as
artifacts and actually we store those
artifacts inside of an artifact
repository so just artifactory Nexus
that's kind of thing we store them in
that artifact repository and then
provide different experiences to pull
whole business units of code in the form
of those lsts and run recipes run impact
analyses as well searches in these sorts
of things across those business units so
that can happen very quickly because the
LST has been stored in memory so one of
the key features of the commercial
counterpart to open rewrite is the
ability to persist the syntax trees did
I understand that correctly that's right
and that leads to these different multi-
repository experiences Mass PR issuance
we are able to select in our idees as
product Engineers a whole business unit
that we work on that might be hundreds
or thousands of repositories and then in
the IDE where you normally would have
like a F usages button you could say
find usages on my business unit and
you'll find all such occurrences in
Repository that I'm not currently
working on so you kind of get a sense of
the scope of a problem similarly for
intention actions in the IDE whenever
you see a hint that there's something to
fix you can choose to fix right there
you can choose to fix in the whole file
that's what the ID normally does or fix
that whole project or you could say fix
on my entire business and so it's that
ability we're really trying to build
these experiences that grapple with the
fact that we don't work on one
repository we work on many repositories
that's the world that we live in sure
that makes a lot of sense I think many
developers will connect with the fact
that their code doesn't live in a single
repo in a single GitHub organization and
so they need a way to span repos and
span organizations when you think about
GitHub itself it really is very much a
single repository experience even to
this day you look at one repo issues are
attached to one repo PRS are attached to
one repo commits are attached to one
repo and so this is the first foray
really I think into multi- repository
action whether that be impact analysis
or remediation you mentioned a while ago
in our conversation that you originally
started working on open rewrite when you
were at Netflix and now there's a whole
company surrounding this ecosystem so
what I'd like to do towards the end of
our discussion today is to talk about
some of the lessons that you've learned
you clearly know a lot about developer
productivity and developer tooling can
you share with our listeners some
lessons that you've learned from
Building open rewrite we've learned so
many I think even though there's been a
lot of static analysis tooling or things
that worked with the code they've been
predominantly scanners they've really
been built to search and to surface
issues that's a lesson I learned
actually early at Netflix before the
company was ever formed when I was
working on engineering tools trying to
move people forward to that new logging
library trying to move people to the
next Java version I also started with
scanners right I started with dashboards
and workshops and what can I do to make
you move forward and I think it's
because of the harsh reality of that
freedom and responsibility culture where
people would say they just wouldn't do
it and you would say what could I do I'm
here on my knees begging you what could
I do to make you move forward and they'd
say do it for me otherwise I've got
something else to do I'm not going to do
it and that's where I think this
requirement of Auto you I mean I was
compelled to it's not like I had a
special Insight was compelled to do this
this kind of thing when we set out to do
auto remediation there was very little
prior art to work with I think we saw
IDE based refactorings on a narrow level
which are really interesting and have
come a long way in the last 20 years but
there was not a lot of like wholesale
framework migration type things to work
on so we're on version eight of open re
right now because I've messed up seven
major times you know at different points
in the last three or four years so
that's an acknowledgement of our own
shortcomings or inability to see some of
the core functionality early on so as a
company we say one of our predominant
cultural tenants are humility and fierce
resolve so we will not stop we're going
to go find the way this compiler works
and we're going to find some way of
exercising it and getting the data out
of it that can be very difficult but we
are always willing to see where we went
astray and I think that's why we've seen
eight versions it's because we're
willing to admit that we're were wrong
and course correct thanks for that
thoughtful and candid response I really
benefited from it I wanted to talk now
perhaps in a more Forward Thinking or
future oriented fashion many software
Engineers are starting to use AI
techniques in order to help them to do
programming or refactoring can you
comment briefly how does open rewrite
fit into this new landscape of AI
enhanced programming so this is such an
interesting question and you're going to
get some answers here you may not expect
but the first thing to say which I think
you would expect is that we ourselves
are Avid users of co-pilot inside of our
company so I see the primary use of AI
and code as an authorship experience
that's accelerating this trend that's
existed for some time of an increase in
the volume of code under management
already so that bank I was referring to
a long time ago the one that fixed these
sonar Cube issues they have 500 million
lines of code right now something like
that and so we had done this exercise I
think in the book that we wrote for
O'Reilly on automated code remediation
to say if I were to print that code out
into books and just stack them end to
end they would extend from Miami where I
live we tried to go up the East Coast
they go from Miami all the way to
Montreal in Quebec and it's staggering
the volume of code that we have under
management so if I'm going to make a
change to that 500 million lines of code
I don't want a system that has a low
probability of hallucination or a low
probability of incorrectness or
inconsistency I need a machine that has
it's almost like a lean six process like
a manufacturing process low degree of
variability High degree of
predictability I need to be able to go
and do that because if I was to use a
probabilistic system to make those
changes then the change requires human
review to scale with it I have to look
at every single to be sure that every
single currence was right okay so we use
AI for code authorship that's been true
for a while I did a study a little bit
ago I wrote just a particular piece of
code and I actually recorded myself
doing it and went back and counted the
number of characters I typed versus the
IDE typed versus co-pilot typed and I
found that I wrote I think 133% of the
code kind of depressing in a way the IDE
wrote 76% of the code and co-pilot wrote
that other 11% so the ID has actually
doesn't get enough credit it does quite
a bit for us already I think AI based
authorship tools are complimentary to it
but they're still authorship experiences
okay so if we accept for a moment that
they are still probabilistic and that's
just fundamentally what they are and so
maybe not the best thing for this like
Mass remediation then where does it fit
in to this refactoring story we've
really found three pillars here and so
pillar number one is where a recipe
which is think of it as computer gets an
AI so right now we're talking a lot
about agents that's AI gets a computer
I'm talking to chat GPT it gets better
at math it gets better at math because
it's using some agent behind the scene
but I'm talking about the opposite here
so a recipe which is a computer gets an
AI to do targeted changes in code we've
had one such example of this where we
had a code base written in French and
that over time the Java doc comments had
become Mis encoded because of encoding
switches in ide and so we were using the
recipe to identify particular comments
that have this problem and then using
the AI to try to find what the original
word was and substitute it in but there
was no chance for it to make a breaking
change because we were the recipe was in
control and only allowing it to make
changes to specific java. comments so
computer gets an AI That's number one
number two I think is interesting is
recommendations or trying to understand
where there's room for improvement and
so in this respect imagine you could
just sample pieces of your code like a
method decoration and say ask a
generative AI like chat gbd you could go
do this right now to say where is there
room for improvement and it's going to
start listing out some things some
things are going to sound crazy some
things are right and so we've been
taking those recommendations and then
matching them to the recipe catalog
those 2 200 recipes that exist
pre-running them and when they make
change then we have a signal that there
is something to do on the code rip large
and then number three would be in code
search and I think this is an
interesting case where if you were to
say to me right now like I want to go
find every place in my code where I
execute an HTTP client call with a
particular header how would I do that I
would have to know every HTTP client
technology I'm using and go search for
usages of those apis you'd have to kind
of exhaustively know the variation in
technology that exists current research
has really around code search has been
focused on finding method declarations
because method declarations have
comments on them so there's a lot of
text to latch onto there's a lot of
human text to latch onto and match
against the query but in our code where
we're using apis we don't have a lot of
text and so there's where the LST can
help where we can be looking at a
particular call site and we can look up
the type attribution look up the Java do
comment and actually inline those
comment
into the block of code that we're trying
to match on and see if that adds to the
AI enough language that it can latch on
to to do that match so three big pillars
of of use cases there thanks for
identifying those three pillars it
sounds like there's really a lot of ways
in which we could fruitfully combine
various types of AI coding assistance
and what is already available to us as
software engineers in the open rewrite
tool absolutely yeah better together as
usual I think that's a good point now as
we draw our conversation to a conclusion
Jonathan is there a call to action that
you'd like to share with our listeners
when it comes to open rewrite or
automated refactoring it somewhat
depends on who The Listener is so I'll
say if you're a framework author if
you're an open source framework author
especially but even if you're a vendor
providing an API to your users think
about providing recipes to your users to
help move them forward with you it's
good for you it's good for your end
users they love you and if you don't
coming for you we're going to find a way
if you're a developer using those
libraries I think go to that docs.
open.org look for recipes that make that
change and start thinking in this way
that you can fix horizontally across
your whole Cod base all right this has
really been an exciting opportunity for
us to learn about automated refactoring
Jonathan thanks for being on software
engineering radio thank you thank you
for having me this is Gregory cap Hammer
signing off for software engineering
radio goodbye
everyone thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by it e software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also o email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening